Most PDFs on the web are inaccessible - making
it so people using assistive technologies
can’t navigate or read them.
In this video, we'll start with what PDFs
need to be accessible.
Then, we’ll manually test an inaccessible
PDF to see how it affects assistive technology
users.
We'll end with why we prefer HTML webpages
to PDFs.
Like HTML webpages, PDFs need alternative
text, correct heading use, the right color
contrast, and other accessibility design techniques.
But, PDFs also need to be tagged and have
their reading order checked.
Tagging tells screen readers what content
is headings, paragraph text, images, and links.
And, the reading order makes sure the content
is read in, you guessed it, the right order.
Most PDFs don't have the right tagging or
reading order, which means they are unreadable
to someone using assistive technology like
a screen reader.
Let's take a look at how inaccessible PDFs
would affect someone using a screen reader.
I'm going to use Mac's VoiceOver screen reader,
and the PDF is opened in Adobe Acrobat.
Where the PDF is viewed and the screen reader
settings can affect the experience.
If you want to try testing your own PDFs,
check out the links for Mac's VoiceOver screen
reader and Window's NVDA screen reader below
- both are free.
Okay, let's get to this example.
This PDF was saved using Print and then Save
as PDF.
When saving a PDF this way, it can make it
so the PDF is one giant image.
The screen reader won’t be able to read
it at all.
Let’s hear what this sounds like.
VoiceOver: Window.
Alert, document unavailable pane.
VoiceOver: Alert, document unavailable pane.
Content is empty.
Since that PDF was saved using Print and then
Save as PDF, it saved the text as an image,
so it is unreadable to assistive technology.
Now, let’s hear a PDF that has readable
text but hasn’t been tagged, and the reading
order wasn’t checked.
VoiceOver: California beaches.
VoiceOver: When you think of California one
of the first things that comes to mind is
its beaches.
Ride the wave and learn more about what beaches
are the most popular and how their temperatures
vary.
VoiceOver: Most popular beaches temperatures.
You'll notice the screen reader doesn't announce
the type of element like headings or graphics,
which takes away the structure.
I'm going to play the screen reader again.
Take a look at what happens when these same
PDF gets to
the columns.
VoiceOver: According to U.S. News the top
three in the table below, the June 2021 California
beaches are temperatures compared for each
of the.
VoiceOver: One.
Two.
Because the PDF's reading order is wrong,
the screen reader reads the columns from left
to right instead of going column by column.
Now, the PDF is tagged and has the reading
order corrected.
Tagging the PDF and correcting the reading
order can be a tedious process the more complex
your documents get.
Okay, let's hear the difference.
VoiceOver: Heading level 1, California beaches.
VoiceOver: When you think of California one
of the first things that comes to mind is
its beaches.
Ride the wave and learn more about what beaches
are the most popular and how their temperatures
vary.
VoiceOver: Heading level 2, Most popular beaches
VoiceOver: According to U.S. News, the top
three beaches are: 1.
Laguna beach.
2.
La Jolla.
3.
Malibu beach.
VoiceOver: Malibu beach, graphic.
Graphic.
VoiceOver: Heading level 2, Temperatures.
Now, the screen reader announces key structural
elements like headings, graphics with their
alternative text, and it's reading the columns
correctly.
As you could tell, even pretty simple PDFs
quickly become inaccessible without tagging
and the right reading order.
So, we suggest HTML webpages instead of PDFs
whenever possible.
Here's why: First, Like we've said, PDFs take
extra work to make accessible.
Second, It can be expensive to remediate complex
PDFs, and Third, PDFs can be hard for any
user to read on mobile.
If you’ve opened a PDF on a mobile device,
you are probably familiar with the pinching
to zoom and finger-scrolling needed to read
navigate PDFs on mobile.
Remember, if a PDF is needed, it needs to
be properly tagged and have the right reading
order on top of all the other accessibility
design techniques.
Otherwise, we suggest sticking to HTML web
pages.